(CLOCK TICKING)
(DISTANT EXPLOSIONS)
(PLANE ENGINE ROARING)
- (CLOCK TICKING ACCELERATES)
- (BOMB WHISTLING)
(SOLDIERS SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
(MUFFLED GRUNTING)
(BOMB WHISTLING)
(STORMTROOPER GRUNTS)
- (EXPLOSIONS CONTINUE)
- (GASPING)
- (SPEAKS GERMAN)
- (MUFFLED GROAN)
STORMTROOPER:
(IN ENGLISH) On your feet!
(SPEAKS GERMAN)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(MUFFLED GRUNTING)
(IN GERMAN) An American, Colonel.
He was at the gate,
impersonating an officer.
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYS)
COLONEL: (IN ENGLISH)
You were alone?
Spy, you were alone?
I like to be alone.
What did you come here for?
You got a lot of nice stuff.
Other people's stuff.
"To the victor
belongs the spoils."
"To the victor"?
Berlin's in rubble.
The Führer's in hiding.
You lost.
(IN GERMAN) Take him upstairs.
(IN ENGLISH) What? What? Hey!
Hey, wait a second. Guys!
MAN: (IN GERMAN)
A moment. Please!
Stop! I must speak to the commander.
Colonel. I found it!
Do as he says. Open it.
Doctor.
DOCTOR: The Lance of Longinus.
The blade that drew Christ's blood.
The Holy Lance.
(EXPLOSION OVERHEAD)
(SOLDIERS CLAMOURING)
Double the guard.
This is the prize the Führer seeks.
Colonel, we need to talk.
No time, Doctor.
The train to Berlin is waiting.
Search the woods!
Take the dogs.
Do you think that spy was alone?
Go! Go! Go! We're moving out!
On the double!
(DOGS BARKING)
(SOLDIERS SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(IN ENGLISH) Looks like
they're leaving
without you guys.
Tell us your story, or die.
Story. Erm...
Okay, okay.
Well... (LAUGHS DRYLY)
It all started
once upon a time,
when this village
of stupid blue-eyed boys
decided to join hands together
and follow this sweaty
little pied piper
- named Adolf...
- (GRUNTS ANGRILY)
(PLANE PASSING LOW OVERHEAD)
(BOMB WHISTLING)
(SOLDIERS EXCLAIM)
(STRAINS)
(CHOKING)
(BOMB THUDDING)
(SOLDIERS SCREAMING)
- (DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
- (GRUNTING)
(GRUNTS)
(GASPING)
(SCREAMS)
(GRUNTS)
(SOFT CREAKING)
(GASPS)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC CONTINUES)
(SOLDIERS SPEAKING GERMAN)
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
(IN GERMAN) This man
was with the American.
This is the American's bag.
What have I done?
Bring him to my carriage.
(STORMTROOPERS SHOUTING)
Careful.
This is the Führer's special relic!
(GRUNTS)
OFFICER: Heil Hitler!
(OFFICERS SPEAKING GERMAN)
(VEHICLE HORN HONKS)
OFFICER: Stay seated.
COLONEL: So...
you are a birdwatcher?
Yes. Because of the bombing,
the wagtails are following
a completely different trajectory.
COLONEL: We caught your accomplice.
The American.
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYS)
(FOREBODING MUSIC PLAYING)
(CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
- (GRUNTS)
- (TYRES SCREECHING)
(ENGINES REV)
(OFFICERS PROTESTING)
- (SHOUTS)
- (TYRES SCREECH)
(ALL EXCLAIM)
(SCREAMING)
(OFFICERS CONTINUE PROTESTING)
(SHOUTING)
(GRUNTS)
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(CONTINUES PROTESTING)
(SCREAMING)
(IN ENGLISH) Oh, my!
(INDIANA YELLS)
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(ENGINE REVS)
(GRUNTING)
INDIANA: Get off of me!
(YELLS)
(EPIC MUSIC BUILDING)
(SHOUTS)
(SCREAMS)
(GRUNTS)
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYING)
- (GROANS)
- COLONEL: There's one reason
you're still alive,
birdwatcher.
Who sent you?
What was your mission?
Please, Colonel, no.
I beg you.
My name is Basil Shaw.
I'm a professor at Oxford.
An archaeologist.
(WIND WHISTLING)
INDIANA: There you are.
(IN GERMAN)
There is a problem.
- I must speak to the Colonel.
- (RESPONDS IN GERMAN)
It's urgent.
(GUARD CONTINUES PROTESTING)
(IN ENGLISH)
I have a daughter. I beg you.
I guarantee you will never see
your child again, Mr. Shaw.
(SIGHS) Unless you explain
why your accomplice had this.
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYS)
BOTH: Sieg heil!
BASIL: We were told
that the Lance of Longinus
could be found
at the fortress.
We were looking for it.
Why?
Because of its power?
(CHUCKLES) It has no power.
My friend and I
were trying to save history.
- (DOOR OPENS)
- (COMMOTION)
(IN GERMAN) I must
speak with the Colonel.
It's about the Lance.
(SNIFFS)
(CHUCKLES)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYS)
(SENTRY SPEAKING)
(COMMANDS)
(SHOUTING)
(DOORKNOB RATTLES)
(SENTRY CONTINUES SHOUTING)
I only had a moment to look at it.
Of course, my training is in physics,
For God's sake, spit it out!
The Lance...
(IN ENGLISH) It's a fake.
(IN GERMAN) It's a fake.
A fake?
The blade is an alloy.
Fifty years old,
the engravings recent. It's a replica.
COLONEL: We're dead.
INDIANA: (IN ENGLISH)
Twelfth century.
Thirteenth century.
Ramesses II.
None of this stuff is fake.
(MUFFLED SENTRIES SHOUTING)
I gotta stop this train.
(IN GERMAN)
There is another relic on this train.
One with real power.
What are you talking about?
The Antikythera.
COLONEL: The Antikythera?!
Enough about that old dial!
DOCTOR: Colonel, the Führer
has lost the war...
and his mind!
Let me explain.
The Antikythera's power
is not supernatural.
It is mathematics.
Whoever harnesses it...
will not be King...
nor Emperor...
or Führer.
He will be God.
(GERMAN SOLDIERS SNORING)
(SENTRY SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
(DOOR BANGS)
(URGENT CHATTER)
(IN ENGLISH) Too many Nazis.
- (ALARM BUZZING)
- (SHOUTS IN GERMAN)
(IN GERMAN) And how do you propose
we tell him this?
My Führer,
I'm sorry the Lance of Christ is fake.
But here is...
half of something you've never heard of.
Tell me,
have you ever MET HITLER?!!
(SPEAKS GERMAN)
A saboteur aboard.
And Hitler's Lance is gone.
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(COLONEL COMMANDS IN GERMAN)
(SOLDIERS SINGING LILI MARLEEN
DRUNKENLY)
(SOLDIER SPEAKING GERMAN)
(SINGING CONTINUES)
(ALARM CONTINUES BUZZING)
(GRUNTS)
SOLDIERS: Sieg heil!
That way!
What are you doing here?!
(IN ENGLISH) What the hell?
BASIL: Indy?
Baz?
BASIL: You're alive!
So far.
I thought I told you
to stay in the woods, Baz.
What sort of a man
hides in a hedge
while his friend
is facing death?
(OFFICER SHOUTING ORDERS
IN GERMAN)
(HURRIED CHATTER)
(SOLDIER SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
This lot are carting off
half the world's antiquities.
I was gonna stop 'em,
but now I've gotta rescue you.
Did you at least
find the Lance?
"At least"?
- (BANGING ON DOOR)
- Well, have you got it?
- It's a fake.
- What?
- (GROANS)
- A reproduction.
(IN GERMAN) Who are you?
BASIL: Indy?
The Antikythera.
Archimedes' Dial.
(BANGING ON DOOR)
Bring it.
(OFFICER SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
(PLANE ENGINE ROARING)
INDIANA: Hurry up, Baz.
(PANTING, GRUNTS)
Give me that.
Come on.
(PLANE FLIES OVERHEAD)
- (CONTINUOUS GUNFIRE)
- (SOLDIERS SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
Get up, Baz.
Follow me.
Towards the gun?
Away from the Nazis!
Those are Nazis!
Get down! Down! Down!
(GUNFIRE CONTINUES)
(GRUNTS)
(GUNFIRE CONTINUES OUTSIDE)
(SOLDIERS GROANING)
(GRUNTS)
(SHOUTS IN GERMAN)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(BASIL SCREAMS)
(BASIL GROANS)
(WIND WHISTLING)
(PANTING)
This way. Come on!
I can't do that!
You wanna stop
for a little lie-down?
(IN GERMAN) They have the Antikythera!
- (YELLING)
- (IN ENGLISH) Easy.
(TENSE MUSIC CONTINUES)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC BUILDS)
(MENACING MUSIC PLAYS)
(GROWLS)
Tunnel!
(GASPS)
- (BASIL SCREAMS)
- INDIANA: Got you! No!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(BOTH YELP)
(GRUNTS, YELLS)
(STRAINING)
(INDIANA YELLS)
BASIL: Indy!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
Get the gun!
Shoot him!
(GROANS) Not me!
- (GRUNTS)
- S-Sorry.
(STRAINING)
(INDIANA CHOKING)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYS)
(GASPING LABORIOUSLY)
To the victor go the spoils.
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYING)
(GRUNTING)
(PLANE ENGINES ROARING)
(DOCTOR SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
(IN GERMAN) Drop the gun.
Give me the Antikythera.
Indy!
(PLANE ENGINE ROARING)
Hey!
(YELLING)
- (IN ENGLISH) Here!
- They can't hear you, Baz.
We gotta jump!
What about my dicky knee?
Ahh!
(BASIL SCREAMS)
Baz!
- Indy!
- Baz!
(SOLDIERS SHOUTING
IN DISTANCE)
SOLDIER: Go! Move! Move it!
Bit rum to go home
empty-handed after all that.
"Empty-handed"?
Not exactly.
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYS)
Archimedes' Dial.
INDIANA: Well, half of it.
Come on, Baz. Let's get home.
(INDIANA JONES THEME
CONTINUES PLAYING)
- (DISTANT TRAFFIC SOUNDS)
- (CLOCK TICKING)
(MUSIC PLAYING FAINTLY ON TV)
(MAGICAL MYSTERY TOUR
BY THE BEATLES BLASTING)
Roll up, roll up
for the Magical Mystery Tour
- Step right this way
- (MUFFLED CHATTER)
Roll up
Roll up for the Mystery Tour
- Roll up
- That's an invitation
Roll up for the...
INDIANA: Larry! Turn it down!
Turn it down!
Hey, Larry!
The Magical Mystery Tour
is waiting to take you away
Waiting to take you away
Roll up
Roll up for the Mystery Tour
Larry!
- Hi, Mr. Jones.
- Where's Larry?
- MAN: Who is this guy?
- It's the old guy next door.
Larry, it's 8:00
in the morning.
- "It's 8:00 in the morning."
- We talked about this, Larry.
Yeah, but that was
- a workday, Mr. Jones.
- This is a workday too, Larry!
Turn on the news.
- It's moon day, Mr. Jones.
- (CHUCKLES)
Moon day?
(MUFFLED YELLING AND LAUGHING)
(SPACE ODDITYBY DAVID BOWIE
PLAYING FAINTLY)
(KETTLE WHISTLING)
And the papers want to know
whose shirts you wear
Now it's time to leave
the capsule if you dare
This is Major Tom
to Ground Control
I'm stepping through the door
And I'm floating
in a most peculiar way
And the stars look
very different today
Thanks.
(GIRLS LAUGHING)
All you really
need to remember
is that Assyrian ceramics of this period
are characterised
by this complex
blue-line pattern.
Okay?
I assigned pages 131
through 171
in Winford for today.
Anybody do the reading?
Anyone?
This is on the test.
Okay.
Guess I'll spoon-feed it
to you.
In 213 BC,
Roman forces led by Marcellus
laid siege
to the city of Syracuse.
"Syracuse."
Not the Syracuse
in New York, Tonya.
The one in Sicily.
Amongst the defenders
of the city
was its most famous resident,
who was...
Come on, guys.
This is on the final.
Archimedes.
Archimedes, who was a...
A mathematician.
INDIANA: A mathematician.
But more than that,
an inventor,
a brilliant engineer
who conceived of a way
to harness the energy
of the Mediterranean sun
on concave mirrors
and focus it
on attacking Roman warships
and set them on fire.
Who devised giant iron claws
that could snatch hostiles
from the sea.
But how do we know
it really happened?
What physical, irrefutable
archaeological evidence
- is there of these inventions?
- The Antikythera.
- For starters.
STUDENT: They're here!
They're downtown!
(COMMOTION)
The astronauts.
REPORTER: (ON TV) Giant parade
this morning will be seen
by about
two and a half million people
lining the sidewalks...
(THE GIRL FROMIPANEMA
PLAYING)
MAN 1: He's coming.
He's come. See?
MAN 2: Oh, here he comes.
WOMAN: Hide the cake.
- Surprise.
- ALL: Surprise!
(LAUGHTER)
(GLASS CLINKING)
For over a decade now,
our colleague Dr. Jones
has been a loyal servant
of Hunter.
A token of our gratitude.
(INDIANA GRUNTS SOFTLY)
Wow. (CHUCKLES)
Thanks for putting up with me.
(ALL CHUCKLE)
(INTRIGUING MUSIC PLAYING)
Here.
REPORTER: (ON TV) Astronauts
Neil Armstrong, Mike Collins,
and Buzz Aldrin will not be
able to avoid the spotlight.
At 11... 00 a.m.
Eastern Daylight Time,
a grateful nation
will pay homage
with a ticker-tape parade
through New York and Chicago,
climaxed by a dinner
in Los Angeles...
What would the ancients say?
ANNOUNCER: (ON TV)
Neil, Buzz, and Mike...
If they knew
we walked on the moon?
Speaking as an ancient,
going to the moon
is like going to Reno.
Middle of nowhere
and no blackjack.
You don't recognise me,
do you?
Whatever I did, I apologise.
It's Helena.
Helena Shaw.
- Wombat?
- (HELENA LAUGHS)
Wow, I haven't
heard that in a while.
- You got tall. (LAUGHS)
- I did.
It's fair to say.
I'm celebrating.
- I'm retiring.
- Oh.
Wow. Well, in that case,
what are we drinking?
Room service for Mr. Schmidt.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
(CORRECTING PRONUNCIATION)
AGENT: (IN ENGLISH) Put that away.
I was asking how you broke
your ankle. (SPEAKS GERMAN)
- (IN ENGLISH) None of your business.
- Are you Mr. Schmidt?
"Doctor" Schmidt.
He's in there.
And he don't eat anything
on wheels,
so put it on a table.
ANNOUNCER: (ON SPEAKERS)
When I was a little boy,
I always imagined
that one day
man would walk on the moon.
And by golly...
Quite a celebration
out there, hmm?
The man you're servin',
he's the one who put
those astronauts on the moon.
Built the rockets
they rode in.
Congratulations.
Where are you from?
The Bronx, sir.
No, no. I mean originally,
your people.
Do you know?
I was born
by Yankee Stadium, sir.
And you fought
for your country?
320th Battalion.
Set up balloons to stop
the planes bombing Normandy.
And are you enjoying
your victory?
PORTER: Will there be
anything else?
You didn't win the war.
Hitler lost it.
(PHONE RINGING)
AGENT: Yeah.
My field agent,
she found Shaw.
Yeah, I'm comin'.
Let's go, Hauke.
INDIANA: Where are we here?
Oxford. In the garden.
(INDIANA SIGHS)
He was an original.
I just graduated.
In archaeology.
Archaeology. Wow.
Apple didn't fall far.
Well, now I'm researching
a doctorate.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY) What's your subject?
The Archimedes Dial.
The Antikythera.
What do you know about that?
Well, for starters,
in 1902, Greek sponge divers
found a wrecked Roman warship,
huge, off the coast of Greece.
Below deck, sealed in wax,
was a clock-like mechanism,
finely tooled,
purpose unknown.
Nothing approximating
its complexity
appears in the world
for 1,000 years.
- You've done your homework.
- Well, not me.
Dad. He had
all these journals,
reams of notes about it.
He was obsessed till the end.
(SIGHS)
He told me you found it
on a Nazi plunder train.
And then lost it in a river
in the French Alps.
Hmm. Well, that was a long time ago.
And it was only half the Dial.
- Archimedes...
- Archimedes broke the Dial...
- ...disassembled it.
- ...in two, and then hid
the two halves from the Romans
during the siege of Syracuse.
I know. Look.
You don't remember the last
time I saw you, do you?
Remember what?
These are the Alps.
Yeah, I see.
And this is the route
that your train took
from the Nazi stronghold
- in '44.
- Right.
HELENA: It went through
this mountain pass,
and then here.
Here, it's the only river
on the route.
- Right.
- Under a bridge.
It's down there.
It's got to be.
- And nobody knows except us.
- "Us"?
Well, I mean, you.
And me. So, yeah.
- Us.
And what were you
thinking exactly?
Well, that maybe...
we could go there.
And?
And find it. And...
And I'd become...
famous.
Oh, well, not famous.
Renowned. Feted.
A feted archaeologist.
And you, a final triumph!
Indiana Jones!
Out with a bang!
Back in the saddle!
(SIGHS)
I'm not selling this, am I?
Wombat...
why are you chasing the thing
that drove your father crazy?
Wouldn't you?
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
I got it.
KLABER:
Parade's comin' soon.
So, what we got?
She's in there, third floor,
with an old guy.
Who is he, a Russian?
No, a professor.
Dr. Henry Jones.
Klaber!
Klaber, get back here!
You're not an agent!
God damn it! Go.
I'll get support up here
and pull a file on Jones.
(MYSTERIOUS MUSIC PLAYING)
INDIANA: This way.
(KEYS JANGLING)
(LOCK CLICKS)
Basil became obsessed
by this German theory.
Conjecture, really.
Archimedes had figured out
that the movements
of the moon and planets
weren't perfect.
There were irregularities
in their rotations.
He thought these
irregularities might
explain fluctuations
in temperature, tides.
Storms, even.
So, he set about building
a device to predict them.
But then, he stumbled upon
a method to predict
even larger
disturbances.
Larger disturbances?
Your father
thought this thing could
predict fissures in time.
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(AGENT SIGHS)
(PAPERS RUSTLING)
- Hauke, if you don't...
- (KLABER WHISTLES)
- Found 'em.
- (PHONE RINGING)
WOMAN: Hello.
- Are you looking for...
- (PAPERS RUSTLING)
Dr. Jones?
Excuse me, can I help you?
No, thank you.
Just a routine investigation,
ma'am.
Are you the police?
It'll just be a few moments.
- Professor Plimpton.
- Ma'am.
- Professor Plimpton!
- Ma'am!
(SILENCED GUNSHOT)
Drop your weapon.
What the hell are you doin'?
Erm...
What the doctor tells me,
Miss Mason.
PLIMPTON: Mandy?
(SILENCED GUNSHOT)
Yeah, no witnesses.
(LIFT DINGS)
Jesus. What the hell?
INDIANA: Your father wrote
so many letters
about the Dial,
I stopped reading 'em.
You really don't remember
the last time
I was at your house?
I took that from him then.
I thought he'd stopped
thinking about it.
But your father was convinced
this thing was real
and dangerous.
(WHISPERING) Do not shoot.
He was terrified that if somebody found
this legendary tablet,
the Grafikos...
The tablet
containing directions
to the rest of the Dial.
And if they found
the Grafikos,
they might acquire
the other half of the Dial
and put the two together.
I knew
you wouldn't destroy it.
How did you know
he asked me to destroy it?
- What?
- You do remember that night.
(CHUCKLES NERVOUSLY)
I was 12 years old, Indy.
You knew we didn't drop it
in a river.
- Baz didn't tell you that.
- See, listen.
- I didn't...
- No, he never lied.
- No...
- What was all that crap
- about the map?
- You...
No, you've had
too many whiskeys.
What are you doing, Wombat?
KLABER: Stay where you are.
Don't move.
- Who are these people?
- We need to get out of here.
Are they with you?
MASON: Not an inch, Miss Shaw.
Miss Shaw, stop!
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
Helena!
Stop!
Sorry.
- Helena!
- Dr. Jones. It's over.
Who are you people?
What do you want?
MASON: Stop!
Helena Shaw!
She's on the roof.
Find another way up.
MASON: Dr. Jones!
Dr. Jones,
we're not gonna hurt you.
(GRUNTS)
(SCREAMS)
(RADIO CHATTER)
MAN 1: Move.
We gotta follow 'em.
MAN 2: Go. Hurry up.
(BREATH SHUDDERS)
(OMINOUS MUSIC PLAYING)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
Fan out!
(MARCHING BAND PLAYING)
MAN 1: All right, let's go.
Move, move, move! Pack it up!
MAN 2: Come on,
get everything.
KLABER: Found her!
(PANTING)
(CONTINUES PANTING)
(GLASS SHATTERS)
(LINE RINGS)
- OPERATOR: Operator.
- I need the police.
Hunter College.
People are dead.
- Please...
- MAN: Hang up, fella.
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
Stand up.
Okay, okay.
(BAGPIPES PLAYING)
(CROWD CHEERING)
She's gone. You blew it,
you trigger-happy cracker.
- She had it in her hand.
- We got the professor.
(INDIANA GRUNTING)
MAN: Here's the file on Jones.
Yes.
Who are you?
That's my question.
(CROWD CHEERING)
You're CIA.
Oh, not me, man.
I don't take government jobs.
Okay.
How are you acquainted
with Miss Shaw?
She's my goddaughter.
I haven't seen her
in 18 years.
Why did you
meet with her today?
To give her the Dial?
Lady, it's an ancient
hunk of gears.
Half a hunk.
Oh, it's a lot more than that.
(BRAKES SQUEAL)
POLICE OFFICER: Whoa, whoa, whoa!
Where do you think
you're going?
I got a parade going on.
And a demonstration
coming down here.
Hey! Hey, hey!
- Hey...
- Shut up.
I can't go this way.
Gotta go back.
- (CAR HORN HONKS)
- (KLABER GRUNTS)
Hell no!
What is wrong with you, man?
Damn it! Let's go on foot.
KLABER: You heard her.
DRIVER: What the hell
were you thinking?
- Walk! Come on.
- DRIVER: What is your problem?
You don't look
when you're backin' up?
- Take care of that guy.
- Who's gonna pay for that?
Easy, fella. Easy.
KLABER: Keep movin'.
DRIVER: Can't you see my cab?
It's yellow.
No, you're gonna have to pay
for this bodywork, man.
I don't...
(PROTESTORS CHANTING)
PROTESTORS: Peace now!
Peace now!
Stop the war!
Stop the fighting!
- Where are we going, Mason?
- This way.
- Hell no, we won't go.
- Shut up.
- Hell no, we won't go!
- PROTESTOR: Hell no!
We won't go!
- Hell no, we won't go!
- Hell no...
- Shut up!
PROTESTOR 2: Hell yeah!
PROTESTORS:
Hell no, we won't go!
Hell no...
(PROTESTORS SCREAM)
(MASON GRUNTS)
- (KLABER GRUNTS)
- INDIANA: Hey!
Officer! Help me!
(BREATHLESSLY) Officer,
there was a shooting...
- All right, all right.
- ...this morning at Hunter.
People are dead. God damn it.
Some rogue maniacs
broke in and...
Sir, you need to calm it down.
INDIANA: Please listen to me.
There was a shooting
this morning, and the...
They're in a Con Ed van
right around the corner!
(WOMAN SCREAMS)
MAN: Hey! What do you think
you're doing?
(HORSE NICKERS)
(ENGINE REVS)
(PLAYING TRIUMPHANT MUSIC)
BAND: Whoa!
- Watch out!
- What's he doin'?
Whoa!
(BAGPIPES PLAYING)
(TYRES SCREECHING)
- (DRIVER YELLS)
- (BEAUTY QUEEN GASPS)
(SCREAMING)
(FL YME TO THEMOONBY TOM
JONES PLAYING ON SPEAKERS)
(BEAUTY QUEEN
CONTINUES SCREAMING)
Hyah! Hyah!
- (TYRES SCREECH)
- (CONTINUES SCREAMING)
MASON: Move, out the way!
CROWD: Whoa, whoa!
- Hyah!
- (PEOPLE EXCLAIM)
(GRUNTS)
MAN 1: Watch out!
INDIANA: Hyah!
Whoa. Whoa.
MAN 2: Move! Quickly!
(HORSE NICKERS)
INDIANA: (GRUNTS) Hyah!
(PEOPLE SCREAMING
AND SHOUTING)
Move! Move!
(TYRES SQUEAL)
(WOMAN SCREAMS)
(TRAIN WHEELS SQUEALING)
Go, go, go!
(TRAIN HORN BLARING)
Hyah!
(WOMAN SCREAMS)
(PEOPLE EXCLAIMING)
MAN 3: Come on.
That's ridiculous.
- It's a horse.
- INDIANA: Come on.
(PEOPLE PROTESTING)
- Hey, mister.
- MASON: Move! Out of the way!
- Hold my horse.
- Move! Move!
ANNOUNCER: (ON PA)
Transfer is available
for IND Queens Boulevard.
Next stop, 59th,
Lexington Avenue.
- Subway is faster.
- Oh!
People tend
to romanticise science,
when it is, in fact,
quite cold.
REPORTER: So, what's next,
Dr. Schmidt?
Mars?
No, we've conquered space.
I'm moving
to the next frontier.
What's beyond space?
You might wanna
get that suit pressed,
Dr. Schmidt.
We leave for the airport
in an hour.
He's gonna meet the President.
If the President objects
to a few creases,
perhaps he should find himself
another physicist.
REPORTER: Can I use that?
BAXTER: No.
Yes.
- (PHONE RINGING)
- Baxter.
It's for you, Doctor.
I may wanna leave a bit later
for Los Angeles.
I'm expecting
a delivery shortly.
Speak.
MASON: (ON PHONE)
Your goons made a mess.
DR. SCHMIDT: Did they?
Miss Shaw met
with a professor. Jones.
She acquired the device
from him.
Then we lost her.
Dr. Jones got away as well.
DR. SCHMIDT: Is that so?
Most unfortunate.
I gotta clean things
up here, Doctor.
And as a representative
of the United States
government,
I urge you to cooperate.
Get on that plane
to Los Angeles,
and get your medal
from the President.
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(HANGS UP)
Hello?
Call our friends
and secure a private charter.
To Morocco.
Yes, sir.
REPORTER: (ON TV)
The university murders
took place at the height
of the parade.
Police are searching
for retired professor
Dr. Henry Jones.
A colleague told ABC that
Jones recently lost his son
and was in the middle
of a divorce.
(CHUCKLES) This guy,
he looks like you.
Nah. No.
- It is you.
- No, no, no. Hey.
- Go home, pal. You're drunk.
- This is the guy!
- Hey!
- It's the killer! (GRUNTS)
Sorry I'm late, Indy.
Bridge traffic.
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
Boy, am I glad
to see you, Sallah.
I wish I could say the same,
old friend.
Quickly, Indy. Inside.
Your goddaughter, Helena,
was arrested in Tangier
last year
(SIGHS)
for auctioning contraband.
There's more.
She was bailed out
by Aziz Rahim.
Aziz Rahim is the son
of Big Rahim,
a well-known Moroccan mobster.
Big Rahim
owns the Hotel Atlantique
in Tangier, and this week,
the hotel is hosting
its annual auction
of stolen antiquities.
All the big players
are already there.
Alia, Jabari.
This is the great man
who brought our family
to America during the war.
Quick, when was
the Suez Crisis?
(SCOFFS) 1956.
Very impressive, Jabari.
My grandchildren watch
too much TV,
but they know their history.
They understand what it is
to be American and Egyptian.
I need a ride
to the airport, Sallah.
If you run, the police will
assume that you're guilty.
Without Helena or the Dial,
I'm gonna get framed
for murder.
Have you thought
about calling Marion?
She doesn't wanna talk to me.
WOMAN: (ON PA)
Welcome to New York's
John F. Kennedy
International Airport.
The upper level is
for Pan American Airlines...
I took something else
from your apartment.
It was under the bed.
(WISTFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
Thanks, Sallah.
I also brought my passport.
I could help you.
In Tangier?
Wherever chance takes us.
Indy, I...
I miss the desert.
I miss the sea.
And I miss waking up
every morning
wondering what
wonderful adventure
the new day will bring to us.
This is not
an adventure, Sallah.
Those days have come and gone.
Perhaps.
Perhaps not.
Give 'em hell, Indiana Jones!
(TYRES SCREECH)
Champagne?
We've got four more hours
to Tangier.
Your scotch, sir.
Thanks.
(SOFT KNOCKING)
Basil. Come on, Baz!
- Open the door!
- BASIL: No!
- Stay out, Indy!
- Open the door.
- (DOOR SCRAPES)
- (BOTTLES CLINKING)
The Germans were right, Indy.
- INDIANA: Huh? What?
- It's too big. It's too much.
Hey, Ba... Hey, hey! Hey, Baz!
- Give me...
- No.
What are you doing?
You've listened
to nothing that I said.
I don't understand it, Baz!
Well, I was trying to
explain it to you downstairs.
You've just
ignored everything.
You're terrifying
your daughter.
Indy, Archimedes
discovered
a temporal meteorology.
Archimedes was
a mathematician, Baz,
not a magician.
He could predict
fissures in time.
(CHUCKLES) Fissures in time?
- Baz, you can't prove that!
- Well, not yet.
Proving it
is what makes it science!
(CHUCKLES RUEFULLY)
(PENSIVE MUSIC PLAYING)
Oh, Baz.
I never should've
given you the thing.
It... It belongs in a museum.
Give it to me. Please.
(BREATHING SHAKILY)
If I give you this,
it must be destroyed.
I will.
I'll destroy it, Baz.
Promise.
I'm sorry about this.
It's all my fault.
- Are you gonna be here?
- Yes, sir.
Okay. I've gotta catch
an aeroplane.
If anyone finds the Grafikos,
they'll have both halves.
Some things
should stay buried.
INDIANA: I know, Baz.
BASIL: It's vital
that you destroy it.
INDIANA: I will, Baz.
BASIL: Do you understand?
INDIANA: I'll destroy it. Yes.
BASIL: Say you will, Indy.
INDIANA: I will... Yes.
BASIL: You promised me.
Remember that.
I will... I promise.
BASIL: There's a reason,
a reason that Archimedes
broke it in two.
I know, Baz.
- Indy.
- Ah.
Thanks, Wombat.
He's gonna be all right
in a few days.
I'll call you
as soon as I land.
FLIGHT ATTENDANT: (ON PA)
Ladies and gentlemen,
we are 20 minutes
from landing in Tangier.
(SENTIMENTAL MUSIC PLAYING)
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
- Stop drinking!
- What are you doing?
No more champagne!
How many more...
WOMAN: I'm staying.
Go home. Go home!
(CHOMBO MERINGUEBY LES
AIGLONS DE BASSE TERRE PLAYS)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(SPEAKING ARABIC)
(IN ENGLISH) Rahim.
Miss Shaw, she's here.
(SPEAKING ARABIC)
HELENA: Forged in bronze.
Nearly complete.
It is an astrological clock.
Dating third century BC
and built
by Archimedes himself.
AUCTIONEER: All right,
let's start at 20,000.
20,000, thank you very much.
30.30.
Gauges green, power full,
and when I reach 85, I rotate.
What next?
Louis, help him! He's so cute.
- Pull back on the yoke.
- I did, man. I'm airborne.
Yeah, he's airborne.
- Can I have a sip?
- Do I pick up the flaps?
Don't touch the flaps
under 400 feet.
Decrease your pitch
to get to 120.
All right.
- Private auction, old timer.
- I've gotta get in there.
No password, no entry.
I don't make the rules.
DUTCH PRINCE: And, er,
what is the current bid?
- The bid is 50,000.
- Then I bid 55.
(SPEAKS FRENCH)
Who'll give me 60?
- 60.
- 60.65?
- (WOMAN BIDS IN CANTONESE)
- 65.70?
- DUTCH PRINCE: 75.
- 75.80?
- 80.
- 85.
INDIANA: How about 90?
(CHUCKLES DRYLY)
- This auction is private.
- This auction's over.
Au contraire,
it's hardly begun.
- DUTCH PRINCE: 100.
- 100,000.
I like the hat, by the way.
Makes you look
at least two years younger.
- Thanks.
- (MAN 3 BIDS IN ITALIAN)
- 110, bravo.
- I told you that
- this auction is over.
- Excuse me, who is this man?
- I'm her godfather.
- He's mildly related.
And she's up past her bedtime.
- Come on, Wombat.
- I wouldn't do that.
You want to explain it
to the cops at the bar?
The ones I paid off?
You're out of your depth,
Jonesy.
- "Jonesy"?
- He thinks I'm a criminal.
He's the one
wanted for murder.
Nice big picture
in the New York Herald. 130?
I didn't kill anyone.
No entry,
it's a private auction.
INDIANA: And you know it,
Helena.
But whoever did
was looking for this.
What you've got here
is Pandora's Box.
No, actually.
It's my box.
You.
Have we met?
No.
INDIANA: My memory
is a little fuzzy,
but your face rings a bell.
Are you still a Nazi?
(CHOKES, COUGHS)
(SCOFFS)
You're confused.
My name is Schmidt.
Professor Schmidt
of Alabama University.
Professor Schmidt. How nice
to meet you in person.
- (SPEAKING CANTONESE)
- 150.
DR. SCHMIDT: After our conversation,
Miss Shaw,
I thought we'd come to
an agreement about the Dial.
INDIANA: Funny. The last time
I saw the other guy
who looks like you,
he was also after this.
Your numbers were light,
Professor Schmidt.
But good news is, you're here
now. The bid is 160.
DR. SCHMIDT: You don't seem
to understand, Miss Shaw.
This relic is my property.
- It's not yours. You stole it.
- Then you stole it.
And then I stole it.
It's called capitalism.
The bid is 160.
MAN 4:160.
HELENA: 170?
You should've
stayed in New York.
- HELENA: 170?
- You should've stayed
- out of Poland.
- HELENA: 170. Anyone? Anyone?
Going, going...
Gone!
Stay away!
Get the Dial.
(SHOUTS)
(GASPS)
(SHOUTS) Stay away!
- (BONES CRACK)
- (GROANS)
Oh, hello, Claude.
You should not
have come back, Helena.
- (WHIP CRACKING)
- (ALL EXCLAIMING)
Get back.
(GUNS COCKING)
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
Teddy!
(PEOPLE CLAMOURING)
(PEOPLE GRUNTING)
(EXHILARATING MUSIC PLAYING)
(HELENA EXCLAIMS)
Rahim says you stay.
(BOTH GRUNTING)
Thank you.
(PEOPLE CLAMOURING)
See you in the past,
Dr. Jones.
(PANTING)
(HELENA GRUNTS)
(BOTH PANTING)
(SIREN APPROACHING)
It's my cab!
(OFFICERS YELLING IN ARABIC)
(HELENA SPEAKS ARABIC)
Tell them to back off.
(IN ENGLISH)
I just told them to shoot you.
INDIANA: All right, guys.
Put the guns down.
Put 'em down.
All right.
That's better.
(VEHICLES APPROACHING)
Oh, dear.
(CHUCKLES NERVOUSLY)
Rahim.
You're in pyjamas.
I was sleeping, Helena.
HELENA: Mmm-hmm.
RAHIM: Peacefully.
Oh.
My father woke me.
He told me you'd
returned to our hotel.
Then he handed me
this scimitar
and told me to come home
with your head.
Huh.
Does it have to be that bit?
(PANTING)
I thought maybe you returned
because you loved me.
Rahim,
I had an item to sell.
Excuse me. The item
she's talking about
- actually belongs to me.
- No.
You do not need to intrude
in this conversation.
And some very bad people,
worse people...
You do not need to get
involved with my business.
- ...have run off with it.
- Is this your new man?
- No. No, no, no, no.
- It's complicated.
(SPEAKING ARABIC)
What exactly
do you owe this guy?
Just some bail money
and a lifetime of happiness.
I presume you sold the ring.
It didn't go for as much
as I thought it would.
I'll do it!
INDIANA: What are you... Hey!
- (SCREAMING)
- (SHOUTING IN ARABIC)
You just got me killed!
Well, I'm not the one that's
engaged to a mobster!
I don't need morality lessons
from an ageing grave robber!
I'm not a grave robber.
Your father and I
did important work together.
- (GUNSHOTS)
- (MAN SHOUTS)
(GASPS)
Don't tell me
all your escapades were noble,
selfless quests.
You did it for the buzz!
Oh, good work, Teddy!
- Move over, kid.
- Hey!
(ENGINE REVVING)
- Helena!
- Back up! Back up!
Not this way!
You don't know where you're
going, Indy! Listen to him.
- He knows this town!
- I know Tangier!
(TYRES SCREECHING)
There he is!
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
Faster. Go faster!
Ten minutes
to the airport, boss.
(TYRES SCREECH)
HELENA: I'm not sure
Professor Schmidt
is an actual professor,
by the way.
- He's a Nazi!
- TEDDY: Turn left!
Turn left! Turn left!
HELENA: Oh, no!
TEDDY: No!
(HELENA YELPING)
Helena! Don't do this!
(HENCHMAN SCREAMS)
(HENCHMAN GRUNTING)
(GRUNTS)
- Hey, this way!
- HELENA: That way!
No!
RAHIM: Helena!
(TEDDY AND HELENA GRUNTING)
HELENA: No!
(SCREAMING)
(SCREAMING CONTINUES)
What the hell?
- (CAT MIAOWS)
- (CHICKEN CLUCKING)
(CAR HORN HONKS)
Helena!
(TEDDY LAUGHS)
Hey! Hey!
- What the hell?
- (MAN SHOUTS IN ARABIC)
Come on!
Come on. Come on!
(OFFICER SHOUTING IN ARABIC)
(HORN BLARING)
(MEN EXCLAIM IN ARABIC)
- (ENGINES REVVING)
- (TYRES SCREECHING)
You think
he'd be proud of this?
HELENA: Who?
Your father!
His only daughter selling
her soul for bail money!
Sounds quite cool
when you put it like that.
And it's not all bail money.
Some of it's gambling debt
- and some...
- Thank you, Teddy.
- Helena! No!
- (GUN FIRES)
Helena!
How did you end up like this?
Well, you mean resourceful?
Daring? Beautiful?
Self-sufficient?
(TYRES SQUEALING)
(ENGINE ROARING)
(ENGINE ACCELERATING)
- (HELENA YELPS)
- TEDDY: Whoa!
- (CAR HORN BLARING)
- (GASPS)
(TYRES SQUEAL)
- (GUNSHOTS)
- (EXCLAIMS)
Hold on!
Go this way!
There he is.
(CAR HORN HONKING)
- (RAHIM SPEAKS ARABIC)
- INDIANA: Stop!
HELENA: Hey! Hey!
INDIANA: Stop!
- Aah!
- (HENCHMAN GROANS)
(GRUNTS)
(TYRES SQUEAL)
On the left!
Take the wheel, Teddy!
What are you doing?
Getting what's mine.
Helena!
(GRUNTS)
Damn it! You crazy? (GRUNTS)
- (GRUNTING)
- Hey! Helena!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
- Take the gun!
- DR. SCHMIDT: Miss Shaw.
Let go, Miss Shaw!
(HELENA STRUGGLING)
- (TYRES SCREECH)
- (INDIANA YELLS)
(BOTH STRUGGLING)
(GRUNTING HEAVILY)
(HENCHMAN YELPING)
(HENCHMAN GROANS)
(ENGINE REVVING)
(CHOKING) Let go.
Come on! Give me the Dial!
- (GUNSHOT)
- Helena!
- Damn.
- (CRASHES)
- (HELENA GROANS)
Turn back! They went that way!
HELENA: He's gone!
INDIANA: Move over!
TEDDY: Hey!
(TYRES SKID)
I didn't come here to
rescue you from your fiancé!
Rescue me?
(TYRES SKID)
(THUDDING)
I just want the Dial back.
(SCREAMING)
(BOTH SIGH IN RELIEF)
(HELENA PANTING)
(SOLDIERS SHOUTING IN ARABIC)
SOLDIER: Put your hands
above your head.
HELENA: Not the smoothest
break-up I ever had.
INDIANA: If your father
was still alive...
HELENA: Well, he's not, Indy.
TEDDY: Hey, something's wrong
with the engine.
If only there'd been
someone there for me,
some father figure, someone
specifically anointed
for the job.
You have no idea
about the kind...
Don't beat yourself up
about it.
I mean,
what even is a godfather?
Anyway, family never
was your strong suit.
- What is the time, by the way?
- It's...
Hey, no fair.
Give me that back.
That was my father's watch!
Give it back to him.
(TEDDY SIGHS)
You're gonna have
to leave town with me.
Rahim will be
looking for you too.
They'll go to
Tangier airport first,
so we'll need to catch a train
and get a plane
from Casablanca.
- (ENGINE BACKFIRES)
- Whoa. What was that?
Ah.
Damn.
MASON: Yeah.
I know, sir.
Yes... (SIGHS)
Copy.
They pulled the plug.
You got them scared.
Because they don't understand.
No. Because your associates
killed three
American civilians
and blew up
a nationally televised parade.
Because you stood up
the President
of the United States,
ran to Morocco,
and created an incident that
required military extraction!
Then take me to DC,
and I will explain it all.
They want you to vanish.
- We have half the Dial now.
- (MASON SIGHS)
They were just trying
to keep you happy,
letting you chase that thing.
They never cared about it.
DR. SCHMIDT:
They will, Miss Mason,
when they understand
what it can do.
MASON: You put them
on the moon.
They got what they wanted.
All right, buckle up.
We're landing in Spain.
C-9 transport will take you
from there to Maxwell.
I'm not going back to Alabama!
All we need is a vessel to
take us to the Mediterranean.
The Grafikos
will take us to the other...
Please, Miss Mason. Please.
Let go of me, Schmidt.
I'm asking you personally.
You're a piece of work, Doc.
Hey!
(GRUNTING)
(GROANS)
(PILOT GRUNTS)
(WIND WHOOSHING)
(SCREAMS)
(MASON GRUNTS)
(YELPS)
(MASON GROANS)
Schmidt...
My name is Voller.
Jürgen Voller.
(EXHALES)
That's a Sea Stallion.
American helicopter.
Did you know
the Wright Brothers?
- What?
- TEDDY: The Wright Brothers.
Orville and Wilbur.
They invented the aeroplane,
and they lived in Indiana.
Wilbur was born in Indiana.
I'm not from Indiana, Teddy.
And the Wright Brothers were
born during the Civil War.
Oh, I thought maybe you went
to school with them.
(HELENA LAUGHS)
Oh, come on, Indy.
That was funny.
- "Funny"?
- Mmm-hmm.
I'm stuck in Tangier
with a broken tuk-tuk
and two thieves.
I'm wanted for murder.
Nazis have
half of Archimedes' Dial
and your father's notebooks.
I have a copy.
Dad's notebooks.
I made a copy.
- Where?
- (GRUNTS)
You memorised five notebooks?
Seven. And of course not.
Half of them were
as dull as ditchwater.
Just the really
important bits.
Like what?
The location of the Grafikos.
Nobody knows
where the Grafikos is.
- Dad did.
- No, he didn't.
- Yes, he did.
- What's a Grafikos?
It's directions
to the rest of the Dial.
Ask her if she knows
what language it's in.
Ah! It isn't in a language.
It's in a code.
What code?
Archimedes used two codes.
Linear B and Polybius Square.
So, even if you find
the Grafikos,
without me, you can't read it.
(CHUCKLES) Please.
Dad taught me Polybius
when I was nine.
Used to leave little notes
around the house.
"Tidy your room."
"Stay away from my brandy."
What if it's Linear B?
50 quid it's Polybius.
Give me that.
Hey.
HELENA: That won't work.
Moroccan chewing gum's made
from the sap of the Manilkara.
Heat resistant.
Try and start it.
(HELENA GRUNTS)
(ENGINE SPUTTERS)
- Start it.
- I am.
(ENGINE SPUTTERING)
- (ENGINE STARTS)
- Huh? Huh?
- Huh?
- It won't hold.
It'll get us
to the train station.
"Us"?
- You goin' home?
- INDIANA: No.
I'm going to Casablanca.
Then I'm gonna hop a plane
to the Aegean.
Just like you.
What makes you think
we're going to the Aegean?
You gotta get to the Grafikos
before the Nazis.
Archimedes was
surrounded by Romans.
Where else would it be?
The Aegean is huge, Indy.
And you don't
have coordinates.
And you don't have a boat.
(CHUCKLES FORCEDLY)
I've got an old friend
in Greece.
An expert diver.
With a big, beautiful boat
that'll get us there
before they will.
You need me,
and you know it.
(SIGHS)
(THRILLING MUSIC PLAYING)
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYING)
Renny!
Indy?
Indy!
(LAUGHS)
So, that's the expert diver?
Spain's greatest frogman.
(LAUGHING) Hey!
So, Spain's greatest frogman
has a shit boat
and only one good frog leg?
Stop it.
(INDIANA AND RENALDO LAUGHING)
INDIANA: You got
a different boat.
- (GROANS)
- Stop it.
We're going here.
Where they found the first
part of the Antikythera.
But... (SIGHS)
We're going deeper.
Dad tracked down
the old sponge diver
who found the Dial.
He told him
that the wrecked Roman ship
broke up under the sea
70 feet below.
Filled with the skeletons
of over 100 centurions.
That's where they found it.
But he said that most
of the ship had broken off
and sunk to the ocean floor.
Too deep for sponge divers.
So, Dad started wondering
why a Roman warship
would sail out of Syracuse
with 100 centurions on board.
They weren't taking
half a Dial for a joyride.
They had the Grafikos...
and they were looking
for the rest of the Dial.
Your dad was a genius.
Yeah.
He was.
(PLAYING SENTIMENTAL MUSIC)
(SPEAKS CASTILIAN SPANISH)
(IN ENGLISH) Seven of spades.
(LAUGHING)
How do you do that?
Wow. (SPEAKS CASTILIAN SPANISH)
(IN ENGLISH) Do it again.
Pick a card, Dr. Jones.
(INDIANA SIGHS)
Seven of spades!
(BOTH LAUGH)
She's magic.
Trick deck.
No.
I force the card.
I offer the mark,
you,
the feeling of a choice,
but ultimately, I make you
pick the card I want.
"The mark."
(RENALDO GRUNTS)
Yeah. Tomorrow is a big day.
I have to check the lines.
(BOTH BIDDING GOODNIGHT
IN CASTILIAN SPANISH)
(RENALDO BIDS GOODNIGHT
TO INDIANA)
Good night.
You remember seeing any dates
in your father's notebooks?
Dates?
What dates?
These dates.
Written over and over again
in this letter.
August 20th, 1969.
That's three days from now.
And the same date in 1939.
Two weeks before
Hitler invades Poland.
(LAUGHS) Wait.
Now you believe the Dial
has magical powers?
I don't believe in magic,
Wombat.
But a few times in my life,
I've seen things.
Things I can't explain.
And I've come to believe
it's not so much
what you believe.
It's how hard you believe it.
I've seen things too, Indy.
The only thing
worth believing in, ever,
is cash.
(PAPER RUSTLING)
Right.
What if you could
go back in time?
What would you do?
Witness the Trojan War?
Check in on Cleopatra?
I'd stop my son
from enlisting.
Did he sign up to please you?
No, he signed up
to piss me off.
How would you
have stopped him?
(VOICE WAVERING) I'd tell him
he was gonna die.
I'd tell him
that his mother would...
find no end to her grief.
(WISTFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
And that his father
would be...
helpless to console her.
And that the loss would put
an end to their marriage.
You're still wearing the ring.
(SEAGULLS CALLING)
HELENA: Mmm.
(SNIFFS) Promising.
(DIVER SPEAKING ITALIAN)
(SHUTS CABINET DOOR)
(CHUCKLES QUIETLY)
More promising.
Hello.
Get your gear on.
They're waiting.
Hey.
Come here.
Okay.
I'm gonna show you something.
Gosh, this looks important.
(CHUCKLES)
(WHISTLES)
Around the rope...
Now, we are going deep.
Descend fast, and breathe
through these hoses.
Okay?
Ah, stay separate.
No crisscross. All right?
We cannot stay long.
I have a method that
usually prevents the bends.
- Usually?
- RENALDO: Yeah.
I call it "the bounce."
You know, fast down,
three minutes on the bottom,
and then up.
Three minutes!
No one more second.
- Three minutes.
- Yeah, that's right.
- Where is my lighter?
- I don't know, capitán.
- (LIGHTER CLICKS)
- RENALDO: We have to go.
Er, quick question.
What's that?
- They're sharks?
- No.
No, no. No sharks here. Eels.
- Eels?
- Anguilas.
Most are small.
Sometimes they are big.
Two metres.
But if you see them,
stay still.
They bite you,
they lock the jaw. Yeah.
They look like snakes.
No, they don't.
(CLEARS THROAT) Private Brandy
reporting for duty.
You're not coming, Teddy?
I can't swim.
Lucky him.
RENALDO: Everyone can swim.
(SPEAKS CASTILIAN SPANISH)
Reach and pull.
(DECLINES
IN CASTILIAN SPANISH)
RENALDO: All right.
You stay here
with Hector
and watch our lines.
- (OXYGEN HISSES)
- It is time, camarada.
(FOREBODING MUSIC PLAYS)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(MUFFLED INDISTINCT TALKING)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC CONTINUES)
(SPOOL SQUEAKING)
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
Two minutes?
(MUTTERS)
(INDIANA STRUGGLING)
(PANTING AND GRUNTING)
(GRUNTING)
(GROANS)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(INDIANA GRUNTING
AND GROANING)
(HELENA CRIES OUT)
(HELENA GRUNTING)
(WATER BUBBLING)
Hey.
(OMINOUS MUSIC PLAYING)
(MUFFLED SCREAMING)
RENALDO: (MUFFLED) Hurry up!
(ALL GRUNTING)
(HELENA SCREAMING)
Helena!
KLABER: Come on.
That's it. That's it.
That's it.
(HELENA YELPS)
- (PANTING)
- (GUN COCKS)
RENALDO: Who are these people?
Nazis.
First, you return my Dial,
Dr. Jones,
and now,
you bring me the Grafikos.
I'm very happy you're not
wasting in retirement.
I should have retired you
when I had the chance.
Where are your sponsors?
I'm on my own now.
Things move forward,
Dr. Jones.
And sometimes...
they go backward.
(VOLLER CHUCKLES)
Now, let's get comfortable
and have a little talk.
(TAP RUNS)
What language is that?
It's not a language.
It's a code.
Polybius.
You owe me 50 quid.
Not familiar
with Polybius cipher?
No.
But it appears you are.
Read it, please.
No.
(GROANS)
Indy...
(SPEAKING CASTILIAN SPANISH)
- (GROANS)
- (HELENA GASPS)
- (GUNSHOT)
- (INDIANA GRUNTS)
(GRUNTS)
Feeling helpful now?
I am.
I know this stuff backwards.
No!
HELENA: Sorry, Indy.
I don't do noble death.
Just
cold, hard maths.
I crack the code,
help you find the other half.
One hundred grand. Cash.
Helena...
Take it or leave it.
You have a deal.
He'll never pay you.
VOLLER: I think
you will find this is worth
more than your asking price.
(EXHALES)
- Teddy.
- Helena,
don't do this.
(HELENA CLEARS THROAT)
Let's see what we've got here.
"My Makhana..."
That's "machine"...
"lies with me,
in the city I left.
"Where wolves
teach men to walk.
"Under one of nine, I lie."
Only one thing
lies anywhere forever.
The dead. So, if the Dial lies
with him, then...
then this is directions
to his tomb.
The Tomb of Archimedes?
Undiscovered
for two millennia.
"The city I left."
Archimedes lived two places
his entire life,
so he only left one.
Anyone? At the back?
Come on, Indy.
Everyone knows this.
- Even this clown.
- Alexandria.
Full marks. (LAUGHS)
Now, "wolf"
in Greek is "lycos."
Root of the word
"lycaeum"or "school."
And the Doric
for "walking" is...
"peripatio."
Which also happens to be
the word for...
Aw.
I thought you were
a bright spark.
"Peripatio"means "walking,"
but it also means "counting."
So, "Where wolves
teach men to walk"
- could be...
- The School of Mathematics.
Is correct.
Now, the next bit is easy.
"Beneath one of nine"?
There are nine Muses.
The Museon.
The Greek word for the
Great Library of Alexandria.
Which, as we all know,
has nine statues
supporting its roof.
May I?
Thank you.
The nine Muses,
in reverse order,
are Calliope,
Urania,
Polymnia,
- Erato...
- Polymnia.
...and Meli whasisname,
that other one,
Thalia,
Euteroe,
but the first is...
Clio.
The Muse of history and time.
That Archimedes,
- what a clever bugger.
- DR. SCHMIDT: The entrance
to the tomb is by
the School of Mathematics,
under a statue of Clio,
in the ruins of the Great
Library of Alexandria.
Gold star for Dr. Brains.
Teddy!
(KLABER GRUNTS)
The Grafikos, get it!
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYS)
(VOLLER COUGHING)
(WHOOPING)
(HELENA LAUGHING)
I have said it before,
and I will say it again!
When you're
in a tight spot, dynamite.
(LAUGHS)
My friend was just murdered.
Sorry.
You told them everything.
Word for word.
But Archimedes
didn't make it that easy.
The tomb isn't in Alexandria.
(COUGHS)
Go!
HELENA: So, what do you see?
INDIANA: Polybius square.
Made of?
Wax and wood.
Anything else?
It's heavy.
Too heavy.
Give me that.
(BOTTLE OPENS)
(MYSTERIOUS MUSIC PLAYING)
(EPIC MUSIC BUILDING)
This is solid gold?
Ancient gold.
From the Nile.
Hold it, Teddy.
(INDIANA CHUCKLES)
(HELENA CHUCKLES, GASPS)
Sell this thing
and we are out of the hole
and then some.
I have just the customer.
Cranky, old Duchess
in Gibraltar...
- This is going in a museum.
- (HELENA SCOFFS)
Take the wheel, Teddy.
What does it say?
"Search where Dionysius
"hears each whisper
"like a hurricane."
The Ear.
The cave of Dionysius.
Where is that?
In Sicily.
- How much fuel have we got?
- TEDDY: It's full.
(ACCELERATING)
They're heading west.
Not east.
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
(SOLEMN RELIGIOUS MUSIC
PLAYING)
BOY 1: I want the papaya.
BOY 2: How much is it?
(VENDOR SPEAKING ITALIAN)
Take this.
Look at that kid
with the straw hat.
- (BOY 1 LAUGHS)
- BOY 2: This way.
(SHOPKEEPER SPEAKING ITALIAN)
Hey.
- What do you think?
- (SIGHS)
What are we doing?
Waiting for closing time
at the caves.
It's crawling with tourists.
Okay, so he's, like,
running the show now?
He's not running
the show, Teddy.
I just thought we were in this
for all the wrong reasons.
We are.
(CHURCH BELL TOLLING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Most assuredly.
You know he's never gonna
let us sell any of that stuff.
I'm still in charge, Teddy.
INDIANA: Helena,
get over here!
Give me a hand!
Oh, you splurged.
Here's your backpack.
Where's the kid?
- (KIDS LAUGHING)
- (PUPPETEER SPEAKING ITALIAN)
(AMUSING MUSIC PLAYING)
- BOY 2: Hey, watch it!
- (RESPONDS IN ITALIAN)
BOY 2: What's wrong
with you?
(DRAGON ROARS)
(SOLDIER YELLS)
(SEAGULLS CALLING)
(PENSIVE MUSIC PLAYING)
Hello.
Hey.
TEDDY: (GROANS) Let me go!
(TEDDY SHOUTS IN FRENCH)
Let me go!
(MERCHANTS SPEAKING ITALIAN)
TEDDY: Get off me! Let me go!
(GRUNTS)
(TEDDY SHOUTING IN FRENCH)
Hey, hey, hey!
(MAN SHOUTS IN ITALIAN)
INDIANA: Helena!
They've got Teddy.
(CHURCH BELL CLANGING)
They took him
up the hill somewhere.
(WEDDING CROWD CHEERING)
(ENGINE STARTS)
Hey. Hey! Hey!
(SHOUTING IN ITALIAN)
HELENA: What are they
gonna do to him?
He knows about the Ear,
what the Grafikos says.
They're not gonna hurt him.
They're gonna use him
to get the other half
of the Dial.
We gotta get there first.
(TYRES SQUEAL)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
TOUR GUIDE: Colonising queens
built many cities in Sicily.
- The temple...
- Let's go.
TOUR GUIDE: ...is the oldest
of the Greek temples.
The cave's over there.
Could we go
a little faster, please?
The Ear of Dionysius.
HELENA: Wow.
(ECHOING)
"Search where Dionysius hears
"each whisper
like a hurricane."
That's some echo.
Keep making noise till we
find out where it's loudest.
(BOTH SCATTING SYMPHONYNO. 5
BY BEETHOVEN)
(SCATTING ECHOING)
(HELENA CONTINUES SCATTING)
(ECHOES LOUDLY) Stop.
(ECHOING CONTINUES)
(ECHOING FADES)
This is it.
Greek pediment. (ECHOING)
An entrance.
Used to be.
A crescent.
Just like on the Grafikos.
I think there's
an opening up there.
You okay up there?
Yes.
(GRUNTING)
You're not moving.
I'm thinking.
About?
About what the hell I'm doing
up here, 40 feet in the air,
with crap shoulders,
crumbling vertebrae,
a plate in one leg,
screws in the other.
Yeah, I get it. I get it.
No, you don't get it.
You're half my age.
You haven't been forced
to drink the blood of Kali.
No. Fair enough.
Or been tortured with voodoo.
And I'm just guessing,
but I don't think
you've been shot nine times,
including once by your father.
(CHUCKLES)
Dad shot you?
Don't talk to me.
Just go ahead.
I'll follow you.
(MEN SPEAKING ITALIAN)
No, no, no. We are close.
We are close.
Look around you.
- We are close.
- The Cave of Dionysius.
No, no, no. The cave
is closed for renovation.
Oh.
Let me ask again.
Where is
the Cave of Dionysius?
(WATER FLOWING)
What's the matter?
You worried about the kid?
Are you sure
they won't hurt him?
He'll be fine.
He's smart.
Where'd you find him?
He, er... He tried to steal
my purse outside a casino
in Marrakesh when he was 10.
I hit him repeatedly
with my car door,
but he didn't let go
and neither did I.
So, been together ever since.
Thought you were
all about the money.
I am.
Nobody memorises every page
of their
dead father's notebooks
for the money.
Herr Voller! (ECHOING)
They went that way.
(HELENA PANTING)
(HELENA GROANS)
HELENA: Why? (GROANS)
(HITTING FLASHLIGHT)
(HELENA SIGHS)
Come on, come on.
(EXHALES) Let's go.
(HELENA GASPS)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
Oh, my...
(INSECTS HISSING
AND CHITTERING)
- (SCREAMING) Oh, my God!
- (GRUNTING)
Oh, my God!
- Oh, God!
- INDIANA: No, no.
Oh, my God! Oh, my God!
(WHIMPERING)
(BOTH GRUNTING)
Are they off me? Get 'em off!
- No, no. Wait.
- Get 'em off!
- (BOTH GRUNT)
- (INSECT SCREECHES)
(HELENA COUGHING)
(BOTH COUGHING)
(STEAM HISSING)
HELENA: What is that?
- Methane.
- (CONTINUES COUGHING)
Don't breathe.
Don't breathe?
We've gotta get outta here.
(CONTINUES COUGHING)
Athena.
Goddess of war.
(COUGHS)
And reason.
"Under the moon...
"life lies at her feet."
Water displacement.
Get in the pool!
HELENA: Why?
Help me open the door.
Well, they didn't
get out the doors!
Get in the pool!
Okay, I'm getting in the pool.
Help me.
- (GRUNTS)
- Archimedes was fascinated
by water displacement!
(DRAMATIC MUSICAL STING)
(WATER TRICKLING)
(METAL CREAKS, SHIFTS)
(GEARS GRINDING)
(MECHANICAL CLICKING)
(BUBBLE POPS)
HELENA: Whoa!
(HELENA EXCLAIMS)
- (GRUNTS)
- Hey! Get back here! Klaber!
(PANTING)
(GASPS)
You don't need to do that.
(BRIDGE CREAKING)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
Hey!
Give me that! (GRUNTS)
No! (SCREAMS)
(HAUKE GRUNTING)
Leave them.
I said leave them.
(CLICKS)
(MUFFLED SCREAMING)
(GASPING)
Reach and pull.
(MYSTERIOUS MUSIC PLAYING)
(CAPTIVATING MUSIC PLAYING)
Archimedes' tomb.
Grab that corner.
(GASPS)
Indy.
This frieze...
It's a phoenix.
A common icon.
HELENA: No. Look,
it isn't.
This phoenix has propellers.
What's this doing here?
Clocks won't be invented
for 1,000 years,
much less watches.
Archimedes used it.
Dad was right.
It works.
VOLLER: Of course it works,
Miss Shaw.
Mathematics works.
As it conquered space,
it will conquer time.
(GUN COCKS)
You've already
lost your son, Dr. Jones.
Your wife is gone.
Do you really
want to lose your godchild?
For what?
A world that no longer cares
about men like us.
Thank you.
(BLOWS)
(BREATHES HEAVILY)
History's greatest moment.
Its end.
- (TICKING)
- (DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
- (YELPS)
- (GUN CLATTERS)
(BOTH GRUNT)
INDIANA: Throw me the gun!
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYING)
- Get him outta here.
- Teddy.
Teddy! Teddy!
Come on! Go!
This way. Come on.
- Go!
- (SHOUTS)
(GRUNTS)
Indy!
INDIANA: Go!
Go!
- (GUN COCKS)
- Stop!
(BREATHES SHAKILY)
Now what?
Bring him.
Helena, come on!
Teddy, we can't
just leave him.
We're not! Follow me!
KLABER: Come on!
HELENA: Come on.
Teddy. Come on.
We've got a car.
Ah, crap.
(GRUNTS)
(PANTING)
Stay there.
(ENGINE ROARING)
Hop on.
(ENGINE REVS)
VOLLER: The first hemisphere
sets the destination.
The second calculates
the location of the fissure
in Alexandrine coordinates.
Have Messner transpose this
to longitude and latitude,
and transmit waypoints
to the pilots.
- Shortcut.
- (ENGINE REVS)
You got coordinates for 37.07.
So, who is it?
Churchill?
Ike?
Who are you gonna kill
to win the war?
In a few minutes,
with the help of Archimedes,
we shall fly
into the eye of this storm
and cross into
Sicilian airspace
on August 20th, 1939.
We will head north
over friendly skies
with enough fuel
to reach Munich.
My quarry
will be waiting for me
at 16 Prinzregentenplatz
for an update
on his V-1 rocket.
(CAR BUMPS)
What kind of Nazi
kills the Führer?
(SIGHS)
The kind that believes
in victory, Dr. Jones.
Hitler lit a fire that could
have burned 1,000 years.
I saw every mistake.
Every blunder.
And I will correct them all.
History is a long list
of losses, Dr. Jones.
It's just a question of whose.
(THUNDER RUMBLES)
(SHOUTING IN ITALIAN)
Stop! (GRUNTS)
(THUNDER RUMBLES)
(GRUNTS)
(SOLDIER SHOUTS IN GERMAN)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(SOLDIER SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
Teddy.
You think you can fly
one of those?
A Nord?
Sure.
It's not a ringing response.
Well, I haven't flown a Nord.
You've never flown any plane.
(BREATHES HEAVILY)
I'll get it started.
No, Teddy.
Crap.
(SOLDIER SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
(SPEAKS GERMAN)
(BOTH RESPOND IN GERMAN)
(GRUNTS)
(KLABER SPEAKS GERMAN)
(GROANS)
(IN ENGLISH) Fasten
your seat belt, Dr. Jones.
There might be
some turbulence.
(CHUCKLES)
You're German, Voller.
Don't try and be funny.
(ROUSING MUSIC PLAYING)
TEDDY: Come on, big talker.
(WHISPERING IN FRENCH)
(ENGINE STARTS)
- (SIGHS IN RELIEF)
- (MOTORCYCLE ENGINE ROARING)
(EXHALES SHARPLY) Okay.
(ROUSING MUSIC CONTINUES)
(TYRES SCREECH)
Okay. Okay. (BREATHES HEAVILY)
Gauges green. Power full.
And when I reach 85, I rotate.
(GRUNTS)
(YELLS)
Okay, wings down.
Okay, 84 miles an hour.
Rotate.
(SCREAMING)
(GRUNTING)
(PANTING AND GROANING)
(CREW CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
(METAL CREAKING)
(PLANE RUMBLES)
(METAL CLATTERS)
VOLLER: (IN GERMAN)
Time to destination?
NAVIGATOR: 60 seconds.
(CREW SPEAKING GERMAN)
(IN ENGLISH)
Continental drift.
Continental drift!
Archimedes didn't know
about continental drift.
- He couldn't have!
- (PILOT SPEAKS GERMAN)
It hadn't been observed yet.
You're off target.
Your coordinates
are based on markers
that have been moving
for 2,000 years!
You could be off
by 10 degrees, by...
(GRUNTS)
(NAVIGATOR SPEAKING GERMAN)
(IN GERMAN) 30 seconds.
Herr Voller...
INDIANA: (IN ENGLISH)
Your calculations are wrong!
(CHUCKLES)
- Herr Voller...
- (SHOUTS) Will you shut up?
I'm thinking!
NAVIGATOR: (IN GERMAN) 20 seconds.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
(IN ENGLISH)
Hold the flight path!
NAVIGATOR: (IN GERMAN)
15 seconds.
(IN ENGLISH) I don't know
where we're going, Jürgen.
10 seconds.
9!
INDIANA: But it sure as hell
- 7!
- ...ain't 1939!
6!
(IN GERMAN) Turn around!
(COUNTING DOWN CONTINUES)
Abort!
Turn around!
ABORT!!!
PILOT: We're being pulled in!
- (NAVIGATOR SPEAKING GERMAN)
- (HELENA GASPS)
(PLANE RATTLING)
(IN ITALIAN) What are you doing?!
This is my plane!
You're flying my plane!
(NAVIGATOR SPEAKING GERMAN)
- (RUMBLING)
- (ENGINE WHINES)
(NAVIGATOR SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
(GRUNTING)
(WIND WHISTLING)
- (ENGINE WHINING)
- (ALL GRUNTING)
(SHOUTING IN ITALIAN)
We're going to DIE!!!
We need to pull up!
(PILOT CONTINUES SHOUTING)
(BOTH SCREAMING)
- (PLANE RATTLING)
- (SCREAMING)
(PANTING)
(BOTH SCREAMING)
(SHOUTS IN ITALIAN)
PILOT: (IN GERMAN) Restart engines!
(NAVIGATOR RESPONDS IN GERMAN)
(ENGINE SPUTTERS)
(ENGINE STARTS)
(BOTH SCREAMING)
(PLANE RATTLING)
VOLLER: (IN ENGLISH)
That's Sicily.
1939.
(ALL LAUGHING)
I did it.
I did it, Dr. Jones!
PILOT: (IN GERMAN) Setting
coordinates for Munich.
(CREW CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
(IN ENGLISH) Yesterday
belongs to us, Dr. Jones.
(GASPS)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
Those are Roman triremes.
(MEN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
(EXPLOSIONS)
(CHUCKLES)
- (PLANE THUDS)
- (GASPS)
- (HELENA GRUNTS)
- (CREW SPEAKING GERMAN)
(WEAPONS WHIZZING)
Keep it in the air!
(PILOT SPEAKING GERMAN)
(KLABER GRUNTS)
(PLANE RATTLING)
(MUTTERS IN ANCIENT GREEK)
(MUTTERS)
SERVANT: (IN GREEK) Master...
The Romans are getting closer.
They have dragons!
(IN ENGLISH) Amazing.
(MUTTERS IN GERMAN)
- (CREW SPEAKING GERMAN)
- (WEAPON WHIZZING)
Whoa!
Open the door!
(GRUNTS)
(FIRING GUN)
What are you doing?
What are you doing,
you idiots?
They think we're a monster!
Aah!
(CREW SPEAKING GERMAN)
INDIANA: You have
to turn around.
This is the Siege of Syracuse.
214 BC.
You got the wrong war.
(CLAMOURING)
(IN GREEK) Master...
Don't ride out there, Master!
The dragons!!
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
(SOLDIERS SHOUTING IN LATIN)
(IN LATIN)
We must take down their dragons!
(SOLDIER GRUNTS)
(SPEAR WHIZZING)
(SCREAMS)
(IN ENGLISH) Boss!
VOLLER: (IN GERMAN) Change course!
The portal closes in minutes!
I have to go back!
I can't be here!
I CAN'T STAY HERE!!
The plane won't make it!!
(SHOUTS IN GERMAN)
(ENGINE ROARING)
(MEN SHOUTING)
(ALL ARGUING IN GERMAN)
(GREETS IN GERMAN)
(SOLDIERS SPEAKING GERMAN)
(ALL SCREAM)
(GRUNTING)
KLABER: (IN ENGLISH)
Get out of the way!
How do you like that,
you savages?
(SHOUTS)
Sorry, pal, but you're a Nazi!
(YELLS)
(SCREAMING)
What are you doing here?
Rescuing you!
(SHOUTS)
(GASPING)
HELENA: (YELLS) Get him off!
Indy!
(PANTING)
(HELENA EXCLAIMS)
Parachute!
I got a parachute!
Hang on! (GRUNTS)
VOLLER: Let go!
Give me the parachute!
- (GUNSHOT)
- (GRUNTS)
(GROANS)
(WHIMPERING)
- (GROANING)
- INDIANA: Grab it. Hang on!
(INDIANA GRUNTS)
- (BOTH GASP)
- Indy!
(BOTH SCREAMING)
- (SOLDIERS YELLING)
- (GUNSHOTS)
(SOLDIERS GROANING)
(CURSES IN GERMAN)
(YELPS)
(SOLDIERS GROANING)
PILOT: (IN GERMAN)
We're losing altitude!
We're going down!
I've lost control!
(PILOT CONTINUES WARNING)
(GASPING)
(IN ENGLISH) Hey,
those are my friends.
Those are my friends.
We need to help them!
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
Those are my friends!
(SOLDIER SHOUTING IN LATIN)
(SOLDIERS GROANING)
(SOLDIERS SHOUTING
IN DISTANCE)
(BREATHES HEAVILY)
(IN GREEK) Eureka.
(REPEATS)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
(HELENA GRUNTING)
(GROANS, PANTING)
(IN ENGLISH)
He's trying to land.
Come on, Indy. Help me.
Get up. Yeah.
We need to get you
out of here. Okay.
Help me. Sit up, okay?
Sit up. You need to help me.
I know it hurts,
but we gotta get you back.
This is incredible, Wombat.
Incredible.
Yeah, it very well is.
But we have to
get you out of here.
My God.
We're witnessing history.
Reverse these numbers.
They'll get you home.
What?
I'm going to stay.
No. You're not serious.
Wow, you are serious.
(PLANE HITS GROUND)
Indy, you've been shot.
You're bleeding.
You can't stay here.
Yes, I can.
But for what? For...
For a long, painful death
with poultice and leeches?
I've imagined this, Wombat.
Studied it.
- All my life.
- Yeah.
And if you stay here,
you will muck it all up.
And die.
Please, get up.
Helena!
I did it!
Bravo, Teddy! Three cheers!
Okay. Indy, we've gotta go.
Get up.
I need to get you
into that plane, okay?
- We need to.
- No. No.
- Get up. You can... We can!
- (SOLDIER YELLING)
(ARROWS PIERCE)
(IN GREEK) Master!
We have to leave, Master.
(IN ENGLISH) It's him.
(ENQUIRING)
He's asking
how far we've come.
(CHUCKLES)
(IN GREEK) Two thousand years.
We've come...
two thousand years.
But we didn't expect to meet...
the great...
Archimedes.
You...
were always...
going to...
meet me.
(IN ENGLISH) That dial
is a forced deck.
It doesn't take us
anywhere but here.
He built it to get help.
Well, we just scared off
the entire Roman Navy,
so I think
we've helped enough.
(IN GREEK)
Apologies, Archimedes.
I'm a fan...
- but we need to leave. He's hurt.
- Helena.
(IN ENGLISH) He can't
keep that, by the way.
He needs to build his own one.
Helena, we need to go!
Indy, the window is closing!
We cannot get stuck here!
(IN GREEK) I want...
to stay...
with you.
(IN ENGLISH) No, no, no!
Do not say yes!
(IN GREEK) You are a brilliant man...
a wise man...
a genius...
Helena...
a hero to your people.
But he can't help you.
This is your time.
(IN ENGLISH)
(IN GREEK) He must be in his own time
He needs to be in his.
His work is not done.
He needs to go home.
There is medicine at home.
(TEARFULLY)
He cannot die here. He can't.
Helena, get on the plane.
I'll be all right.
No, you won't.
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYING)
I need to do this.
Me too.
(CLOCK TICKING)
(LATIN DANCE MUSIC
PLAYING IN DISTANCE)
(CAR HORNS BLARING
IN DISTANCE)
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING OUTSIDE)
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING)
Good morning.
How's the shoulder?
Better than my jaw.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
Right.
INDIANA: You should've
let me stay.
HELENA: I couldn't do that.
Why not?
Well, for starters, you'd have
changed the course of history.
That's supposed to be
a bad thing?
You're meant to be here, Indy.
Here.
For who?
(PENSIVE MUSIC PLAYING)
(DOOR LOCK CLICKS)
Marion.
Hey.
HELENA: Teddy.
Marion.
What are you doing?
Putting groceries away.
There wasn't a scrap of food
in this place.
No. Really.
Someone told me you were back.
Are you back, Indy?
SALLAH: It was explosives,
and Indy was running,
Marion was running,
and suddenly
the plane exploded.
Indy, you're up and about.
Yes, I am.
Yes.
Why don't we go
and get some ice cream, kids?
TEDDY: But Marion
just bought some.
HELENA: Oh,
I know a better place.
You can never have too much
ice cream, can you?
See you later.
(DOOR CLOSES)
SALLAH: (SINGING) A British
taris a soaring soul
As free as a mountain bird
His energetic fist
Should be ready to resist...
That looks bad.
Does it hurt?
Everything hurts.
I know how that feels.
Well, where doesn't it hurt?
(MARION'S THEMEPLAYING)
Here.
It doesn't hurt here.
And here.
(KISSES)
(MARION'S THEME
CONTINUES PLAYING)
SALLAH: Jabari, Alia,
slow down!
Helena! Hurry up!
SALLAH: (SINGING)
I scream, you scream...
Everybody, slow down.
- SALLAH: I scream, you scream
- KIDS: I scream, I scream
We all scream for ice cream!
SALLAH: Slow down. (LAUGHS)
(CHEERFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(MUSIC SLOWING DOWN)
(INDIANA JONES THEMEPLAYING)